Guide to the Whirley Family Papers, 1853-1998 and undated RL.11315
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
- Nigerian Mission, 1853-1993 and undated
  - Nigerian School Materials, undated (Box 9)
    Indigenous languages student work
  - Nigerian School Speeches, 1971 (Box 9)
    From the Principal's Desk handouts
  - Ogbomosho School Papers, 1970s (Box 9)
    Lecture notes, handouts, exams, student work
  - Olivet Baptist High School, undated (Box 10)
    Oyo, Nigeria; School crest
  - Orashi Delta Students' Union Group Portrait, undated (Box 10)
    Iwo, Nigeria; Baptist College
  - Orientation Conference for Missionary Appointees, 1963 (Box 10)
    Handouts and conference outlines
  - Pastoral Training, 1974 (Box 10)
    Ogbomosho, Nigeria; Handouts, conference outline
  - Photographs, undated (Box 17, Folder 28)
  - Photographs, undated (Oversize-folder 1)
  - Race Relations, 1960s (Box 10)
  - Report of Site Visit, Baptist Medical Centre, Ogbomosho...., 1986 (Box 17, Folder 29)
  - Ridgecrest Conference, 1979, 1981 (Box 10)
    Notes, handouts
  - Royal Ambassadors Pennant, 1963 (Box 10)
  - Royal Ambassadors Purpose Statement, undated (Box 10)
  - Shades Mountain Baptist Church, 1972 (Box 10)
    Alabama; Directory, announcements
  - Southern Baptist Convention West Africa Map, undated (Box 17, Folder 30)
  - Travel Documents, 1961-1963 and undated (Box 10)
    Transportation tickets, maps, brochures
  - Uncaptioned Group Portraits, undated; 3 folders (Box 10)
    No location
  - Uncaptioned Group Portraits, undated; 4 folders (Box 16)
    Iwo, Nigeria; Kaduna, Nigeria
  - University College, 1963 (Box 10)
    Ibadan, Nigeria; Handouts, letters to parents, form letter correspndence
  - Volleyball Cup Group Portrait, 1957 (Box 16)
    Class of 1957
  - West African Association of Theological Institutions, 1975 (Box 10)
    Conference handout
  - Western Division Building Company, 1970-1972 (Box 10)
  - Whirley Personal Effects, 1974 and undated (Box 10)
    Inventory of Whirley personal effects
  - Whirley Day' Scrapbook, 1960 June 12 (Box 10)
    Shades Mountain Baptist Church, Alabama; Contains correspondence between Whirleys and American church congregations
  - Women's Missionary Union, 1959-1973 (Box 10)
    Meeting minutes, administrative papers and notes
  - World Mission Conference, undated (Box 10)
    Broadside
- Printed Materials, 1927-1990s and undated
  Printed Materials includes articles, newsletters, newspapers, pamphlets, serials, books, programs, and church bulletins, mostly published during the Whirleys' time in Nigeria, 1947-1980. The publications are both international and from the United States. Many of the newsletters are from local communities in Africa, including the Girls Auxiliary Bulletin, Helps for Sunbeam Leaders, Lydia Bulletin, Mubi Minutes, and Zambian Gazette. Newspapers include several issues of the Nigerian Daily Times and New Nigerian, as well as newspaper clippings from both American and Nigerian newspapers. Pamphlets include materials intended to be distributed to Nigerian peoples on family planning, sexual health, and various religious subjects. Serials include many publications based in Nigeria, including academic publications by Baptist College, the Nigerian Baptist Theological Seminary (NBTS), and Women's Missionary Union. Books contain several publications written by Nigerian people, with others published by the Southern Baptist Convention for distribution in Nigeria. One text, Onise Alase, is in the Hausa language. Programs contain conference and convention programs from a variety of events in both the United States and Nigeria, most of which are from the NBTS, Women's Missionary Union, and Women's Training a Department (a branch of the NBTS). Arranged alphabetically within material type.
  The church bulletins contain assorted church service programs, including regular Sunday worship and special services. From various churches in both Nigeria and the United States. Many of the Nigerian programs are in local languages such as Hausa. There is one folder of miscellaneous printed material gathered by a colleague of Carl Whirley. Arranged chronologically by decade. Programs for funerals have been placed in their own folder.
  - Articles, 1958
    - West African Catechism, 1958 (Box 17, Folder 31)
  - Newsletters, 1944-1995 and undated; 8
    - Assorted Newsletters from Africa, 1941-1980 (Box 10)
      Religious newsletters from Africa in English
    - Assorted Newsletters from Africa, 1981-1995 (Box 17, Folder 32)
    - Assorted Newsletters from the United States, 1944-1992 (Box 10)
      Newsletters from churches and religious organizations
    - Assorted Newsletters from the United States, 1980 (Box 17, Folder 33)
    - Belief Bulletin, 1983-1988 (Box 10)
      United States
    - Bulletin for Emeritus Missionaries, 1980 (Box 10)
    - The Calvary Baptist, 1954 (Box 10)
      Birmingham, Alabama; The Calvary Baptist Church
    - The Cook Book, undated (Box 10)
      Alabama
    - Facts and Trends, 1969 (Box 10)
      United States; Sunday School Board of the Southern Baptist Convention
    - Foreign Mission News Digest, 1971-1976 (Box 10)
      United States, Updates on missionaries from around the world
    - Foreign Mission News Summary, 1982-1989 (Box 10)
      United States, updates on missionaries from around the world
    - Foreign Mission Week of Prayer, 1968-1970 (Box 10)
      United States, Devotions and prayers
    - Foreign Missionary Intercom, 1980-1995 (Box 10)
      United States, Communicating overseas operations to Southern Baptists
    - Girl's Auxiliary Bulletin, 1966-1967 (Box 10)
    - Helps for Sunbeam Leaders, 1966-1967 (Box 10)
      Nigeria
    - The Herald, 1963-1971 (Box 10)
      Birmingham, Alabama; Shades Mountain Baptist Church
    - Home Mission Week of Prayer, 1960-1971 (Box 10)
      Nigeria; Women's Missionary Union
    - Journeyman, 1968-1969 (Box 10)
      Updates of African missionaries
    - Lagos State Baptist Conference Book of Reports, 1979 (Box 10)
      Yaba Baptist Church, Lagos, Nigeria; Conference report
    - Light, 1983 (Box 10)
      United States; Christian Life Commission of the Southern Baptist Convention
    - Lydia Bulletin, 1966-1967 (Box 10)
      Iwo, Nigeria
    - Mission Morsels, 1959-1994 (Box 10)
      Ibadan, Nigeria; Missionary updates
    - Missionary Intercom, 1971-1976 (Box 10)
    - Mubi Minutes, 1992-1993 (Box 10)
    - Nigerian Baptist, 1971 (Box 10)
      Carl Whirley becomes president of Nigerian Baptist Theological Seminary
    - Nigerian Baptist Convention, 1950-1979 (Box 10)
      Nigeria; Annual session reports
    - Nigerian Baptist Convention Book of Reports, 1963-1984; 2 folders (Box 10)
      Nigeria; Conference reports
    - Samford University Alumnus, 1971 (Box 10)
    - The Outreach, 1987 (Box 10)
      Vernon, Alabama; First Baptist Church
    - Perception, 1974-1976 (Box 11)
      Africa
    - Phi Kappa Phi Newsletter, 1981-1982 (Box 11)
      Samford University, Birmingham, Alabama
    - Theologian News, 1972-1977 (Box 11)
      Theological Assistance Program of the World Evangelical Fellowship
    - Tidings, 1960-1962 (Box 11)
      United States, Agency of the Southern Baptist Convention
    - The Tie, 1944-1982 (Box 11)
      United States, Published by the Southern Baptist Theological Seminary
    - Women's Missionary Union, 1966-1988 (Box 11)
      Ede, Nigeria; Birmingham, Alabama; Quarterly and monthly newsletters
    - World Digest, 1982 (Box 11)
      United States; Monthly newsletter published by Foreign Mission Board of the Southern Baptist Convention
    - Zambian Gazette, 1981-1983 (Box 11)
      Lusaka, Zambia; Newsletter published by the Baptist Theological Seminary
  - Newspapers, 1940s-1992 and undated; 9
    - American Newspaper Clippings, 1940s-1980s; 3 folders (Box 11)
      Newspaper clippings on a variety of topics; many from Birmingham, Alabama. Includes Baptist Witness, The Alabama Baptist, The Birmingham News, Problems with the Christian Life
    - American Newspaper Clippings and Magazine, 1964-1992 (Box 17, Folder 34)
    - Nigerian Newspaper Clippings, 1960s (Box 11)
      Includes Daily Sketch, Daily Times, New Nigerian, Nigerian Tribune, Headlines,
    - Obituaries Clippings, 1975-1979 and undated (Box 11)
      United States and Nigeria
    - Daily Times, 1966-1975; 2 folders (Box 11)
      Nigerian newspaper. Most issues are from 1966
    - New Nigerian, 1966; 2 folders (Box 11)
      Nigerian newspaper, daily, morning, and evening editions
    - Samford Today, 1980 (Box 11)
      Monthly university publication
  - Pamphlets, 1934-1977 and undated; 10
    - African Continent, 1963-1985 (Box 11)
      Subject information on Nigeria and the African continent
    - Assorted Religious Pamphlets, 1972 and undated; 2 folders (Box 11)
      Topics on various religious subjects, including: stewardship, youth ministery, vocation, heaven, science or religion, spiritual development
    - Assorted Religious Pamphlets, 1934-1974 (Box 17, Folder 35)
      Missions in Nigeria, prayer, pamphlet in Hausa
    - Baptist Faith, 1945-1963 (Box 11)
      Specific to the Baptist faith, including: Baptist Ideals; Baptists, Roman Catholics, and Religious Freedom, The Baptist Faith and Message
    - The Bible Speaks On…, undated (Box 11)
      United States, Christian Life Commission of the Baptist General Convention of Texas; Topics include race, sex, economcis, christian life, war and peace
    - Christian Principles According To…, undated (Box 11)
      United States, Christian Life Commission of the Baptist General Convention of Texas; Topics include Daily Work, Citizenship, Race
    - Family Planning, undated (Box 11)
      Subject information on family planning. Intended for Nigerian distribution
    - Health, 1943-1977 (Box 11)
      Subject information on a variety of helth topics, including: angina, first aid, measles, smallpox, tuberculosis, health for girls and boys
    - History of Baptist Work at Iwo, Nigeria, 1922-1941 (Box 11)
      Historical account in pamphlet form
    - Issues and Answers, undated (Box 11)
      United States, Christian Life Commission of the Southern Baptist Convention; Topics include communisim, drugs, poverty, pornography, race relations, juvenile delinquency, gambling, mass media, abortion, urban crisis, black power
    - The Radio Committee Sermons, 1944-1945 (Box 11)
      Atlanta, Georgia, Southern Baptist Convention; Sermon transcripts on a variety of religious topics
    - A Souvenir of the Baptist Hour, 1943-1945 (Box 11)
      Atlanta, Georgia, Radio Committee; Sermon transcripts on a variety of religious topics
    - Tithing, undated (Box 11)
      Subject information on tithing to the church
    - What Christians Should do About…, undated (Box 11)
      United States, Christian Life Commission of the Baptist General Convention of Texas; Topics include communism
  - Serials, 1945-1984; 11
    - All Africa Conference of Churches Bulletin, 1974 (Box 12)
      Nairobi, Kenya
    - Africa Report, 1966-1967 (Box 12)
      Washington D.C.
    - Assorted Serials, 1945-1984; 2 folders (Box 12)
      Both United States and international publications on both religious and non-religious topics
    - College Observer, 1954-1968 (Box 12)
      Baptist College; Iwo, Nigeria
    - The Commission, 1953-1980; 3 folders (Box 17, Folder 36-38)
      United States, Southern Baptist Foreign Missions Journal
    - The Commission, 1964-1973 (Box 12)
    - Drum, 1964-1966 (Box 16)
      Nigeria; Special Christmas 1964 issue
    - Editorial Research Reports, 1968 (Box 12)
      Nigeria at War by Russell Warren Howe
    - Evangelism Plan Book, 1967-1970 (Box 12)
      Atlanta, Georgia; Division of Evangelism, Home Mission Board
    - Nigerian Baptist, 1971 (Box 17, Folder 39)
      Photocopied article on Carl Whirley
    - Ogbomosho Journal of Theology, 1989-1991 (Box 12)
      Ibadan, Nigeria
    - Proclaim, 1972-1978 (Box 12)
      Women's Missionary Union
    - Review and Expositor, 1968-1975; 2 folders (Box 12)
      Louisville, Kentucky
    - The Theologue, 1973-1978 (Box 12)
      Ogbomosho, Nigeria; Students of the Nigerian Baptist Theological Seminary
    - WMS Magazine, 1965-1967 (Box 17, Folder 40)
      Baptist Women's Missionary Union of Nigeria
    - WMS Magazine, 1966-1970 (Box 12)
  - Books, 1946-1986 and undated; 12
    - Adult Literacy Education Handbook, 1965 (Box 12)
      Nigerian Baptist Convention
    - Africa: Arrows to Atoms (Box 18)
      by V. Lavell Seats
    - Baptist Women of Ghana, undated (Box 13)
      Weekly programs
    - Bible Heroes, undated (Box 13)
      United States, Southern Baptist Convention Press; Written by Ethel Hudson Williams
    - The Bible Translator, 1950 (Box 12)
      London; United Bible Societies
    - Black Eagle (Box 18)
      by Marjorie Jones
    - Christian Home Week, undated (Box 13)
    - Church Members' Handbook, 1946 (Box 12)
      Washington D.C.; Pentworth Baptist Church
    - Church and Community Survey Workbook, 1970 (Box 12)
      United States; Convention Press; A guide for identifying church needs
    - Daily Bible Readings with Notes for Homes in Nigeria for 1984 (Box 18)
      by Dr. W. R. Ola. Ojo
    - Growing in Knowledge of the Bible, undated (Box 13)
      United States, Southern Baptist Convention Press; Written by Helen Cannon Graves
    - Hausa-English Dictionaries and Grammar Books, 1959-1980 (Box 12)
    - Humanist Manifestos I and II, 1980 (Box 12)
      Buffalo, New York; Prometheus Books; Edited by Paul Kurtz
    - Manual for Missionaries, 1975 (Box 12)
      United States; Foreign Mission Board
    - A Measure of Success, 1986 (Box 17, Folder 41)
      by Roberta McBride Damon
    - Men Who Told His Story, undated (Box 13)
      United States, Southern Baptist Convention Press; Written by Johnnie Human
    - Missionary Paul, undated (Box 13)
    - Missions for Tomorrow (Box 18)
      by Bill O'Brien
    - My Life, 1962 (Box 12)
      Written by Alhaji Sir Ahmadu Bello
    - The New English Bible, 1970 (Box 12)
      Oxford Press
    - Personal Service Plans, undated (Box 12)
    - Onise Alase, 1973 (Box 12)
      Nigeria; Ihinrere Nipa Jesu Kiristi, Nigerian language
    - Religion of the Yorubas (Box 18)
      by J. Olumide Lucas
    - Safari for Souls with Billy Graham in Africa, undated (Box 12)
      Written by Tom McMahan
    - Sick and Ye Visited Me (Box 18)
      by Franklin T. Fawler, M.D.
    - Strategy Program Base Design, 1982 (Box 13)
      Ibadan, Nigeria; Baptist Mission of Nigeria
    - The Story of St. Savior's Colonial Church, 1952-1953 (Box 13)
    - A Study in the Growth of the Nigerian Baptist Convention, undated (Box 13)
      Ibadan, Nigeria; Written by Dr. J.T. Ayorinde
    - "The Sunday School": A Priceless Heritage of the Nigerian Baptists, undated (Box 13)
      Written by I.A. Adedoyin
    - Touch Typing Made Easy, 1957 (Box 13)
      Written by G.B. Wright
  - Church Bulletins, 1927-1990s and undated; 13
    - American Programs, 1927-1990s and undated; 7 folders (Box 13)
      Assorted church service programs, including regular Sunday worship and special services. Majority of the programs are from Alabama.
    - Funeral Programs, 1970-1991 (Box 13)
      Church service programs from funerals in Nigeria and the United States
    - Nigerian Programs, 1950s-1970s; 8 folders (Box 13)
      Assorted church service programs, including regular Sunday worship and special services. From various churches in Nigeria. Majority of the programs are in English, but many are in local languages.
    - Nigerian Programs, 1963-1973 (Box 17, Folder 42)
    - Nigerian Programs, 1980s (Box 14)
    - Undated Programs (Box 14)
      Assorted church programs from both Birmingham, Alabama and Ogbomosho, Nigeria.
  - Programs, 1941-1984 and undated; 14
    - Assorted Convention Programs, 1941-1979 (Box 14)
      Assorted conventions, including several from Nigeria.
    - Baptist Student Conference, 1970 (Box 14)
      Ede, Nigeria; Convention program
    - Baptist Training Union, 1954-1976 (Box 14)
      Iwo, Nigeria; Convention programs
    - Covenant Church, undated (Box 14)
      Birmingham, Alabama; Welcome packet
    - Foreign Mission Board, 1955-1965 (Box 14)
      United States; Conference programs
    - Governor Adeloayo's Farewell Tour, 1971 (Box 14)
      Nigeria; Programme for his farewell tour
    - Nigerian Baptist Convention Assorted Programs, 1969-1980 (Box 14)
      Nigeria; Programs for assorted conventions
    - Nigerian Baptist Convention Services, 1970-1977 (Box 14)
      Nigeria; Programs for assorted church services at the Nigerian Baptist Conventions
    - Nigerian Baptist Theological Seminary, 1957, 1971 (Box 17, Folder 43)
      Ogbomosho, Nigeria. 60th Anniversary Program, 1971 Inaugural Ceremonies
    - Nigerian Baptist Theological Seminary, 1967-1984 (Box 14)
      Ogbomosho, Nigeria; Assorted bulletins and programs
    - Nigerian Baptist Theological Seminary Pastor's Conference, 1969-1978 (Box 14)
      Ogbomosho, Nigeria; Assorted programs
    - Women's Missionary Union-Nigeria, 1959-1979 (Box 14)
      Nigeria; Assorted convention programs
    - Woman's Missionary Union-United States, 1955-1984 (Box 14)
      United States; Assorted conference programs and directory
    - Women's Training Department, 1973-1978 (Box 14)
      Ogbomosho, Nigeria; Nigerian Baptist Theological Seminary, assorted programs
  - Miscellaneous, 1955-1986 and undated
    - Printed Religion Materials from Bill (Cowley), 1955-1986 and undated (Box 17, Folder 44)
      Includes an theological essay by Nels Ferré, a paper on the Okunovu of Idjerhe, a Samford University Library Special Collection register for materials on the Nigerian Baptist Theological Seminary, a Religion 102 Outline of the Interbiblical Period and Genealogy of the English Bible, a program for the Phi Kappa Phi Samford University Chapter initiation banquet in 1986, a copy of Biblical Illustrator (Summer 1985), handouts regarding witnessing to world religions, and a paper on changes in the form of passage rites in contemporary Nigeria.
- Personal Materials, 1937-1994 and undated
  Personal Materials contains ephemera related to the Whirley's personal lives, as well as papers from after their retirement as missionaries. Personal papers include: homemade mad libs, meal schedules from the 1970s while at the Nigerian Baptist Theological Seminary, a hospital visitor's book from Carl's hospital stay in 1975, and miscellaneous family snapshots. Papers from their activities following retirement include conferences and retreats they attended, church council meeting minutes, church building plans, and itineraries from United States speaking trips. The series also contains reports from the Louisville Baptist Orphan's Home and Kentucky Baptist Children's Home at Glendale from 1943, when both Carl and Enid were students at Howard College. Arranged alphabetically by folder title.
  - Carl and Enid Whirley Mad Libs and Meal Schedule, 1976 and undated (Box 14)
  - Carl and Enid Whirley United States Trips, 1980s (Box 14)
    Itineraries, brochures, maps
  - Carl Whirley Passport and Travel Documents, 1954-1984 (Box 18, Folder 2)
  - Certificates and awards, 1979, 1982 (Box 18, Folder 3)
  - Church Building Plans, 1994 and undated (Box 15)
    Birmingham, Alabama: Baptist Church of the Covenant; Fort Walton Beach, Florida: First Baptist Church
  - Church Council, 1982-1983 (Box 15)
    Birmingham, Alabama; meeting minutes
  - Deacon's Retreat, 1982, 1983 (Box 15)
    Riverside, Alabama; Cook Springs; notes and handouts
  - Carl and Enid Whirley Diaries, 1954-1980 (Box 18, Folder 1)
  - Carl and Enid Whirley Diaries and Spiral Notebooks, 1947 and undated (Box 15)
  - Draft Whirley Memory Book, undated (Box 18, Folder 4)
  - Enid Leolyn Pate High School Diploma, 1937 (Box 16)
    Birmingham Public Schools, Alabama
  - Enid Whirley Passport and Travel Documents, 1954-1984 (Box 18, Folder 5)
  - Enid Whirley Press Release, 1963 (Box 18, Folder 6)
  - Foreign Mission Fellowship Conference, 1981 (Box 15)
    Shocco Springs, Alabama; meeting agendas, directory
  - Great Truths of Life, undated (Box 18, Folder 7)
    by Doris McGee
  - Helena Baptist Church Constitution, undated (Box 15)
  - Carl Whirley Hospital Visitor Book, 1975 (Box 15)
  - International Recipes, 1982-1995 (Box 18, Folder 8)
  - Journeyman Memory Book, 1968; 2 folders (Box 18, Folder 9-10)
  - Louisville Baptist Orphan's Home and Kentucky Baptist Children's Home, 1943-1944 (Box 15)
    Louisville, Kentucky and Glendale, Kentucky; Visitor reports and pamphlet
  - Miscellaneous Documents, 1959 and undated (Box 15)
  - Mscellaneous Family Snapshots, 1971-1974 and undated (Box 15)
  - Missionary Kids Directories, 1988 (Box 18, Folder 11)
  - Pine Grove Baptist Church Notes, 1986-1987 and undated (Box 18, Folder 12)
  - Carl and Enid Whriley Resumes, undated (Box 18, Folder 13)
  - To His Glory Memory Book, 1997 (Box 18, Folder 14)
    by Doris and John McGee
- Audiovisual Materials, 1988
  This series contains a videocasette copy of the video "Baptist Missionaries in Nigeria," produced in 1988.
  Conditions Governing Access
  Original audiovisual materials are closed to use. Contact Research Services to request the production of use copies.
  - Baptist Ministries in Nigeria, 1988; 1 VHS (Box 18, Video-cassette RL-11315-VHS-001)
    For use with the Foreign Mission Study